<article xmlns="http://www.erudit.org/xsd/article" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.erudit.org/xsd/article http://www.erudit.org/xsd/article/3.0.0/eruditarticle.xsd" qualtraitement="minimal" idproprio="66175ac" typeart="article" lang="fr en" ordseq="5" idref="th1">
  <admin>
    <infoarticle>
      <pagination>
            <ppage>18</ppage>
            <dpage>22</dpage>
            
            
            
        </pagination>
    </infoarticle>
    <revue id="espace1041666" lang="fr en">
      <titrerev>Espace Sculpture</titrerev>
      <titrerevabr>espace</titrerevabr>
      <idissn>0821-9222</idissn>
      <idissnnum>1923-2551</idissnnum>
      <directeur sexe="masculin">
        <nompers>
          <prenom>Serge</prenom>
          <nomfamille>Fisette</nomfamille>
        </nompers>
      </directeur>
      <redacteurchef typerc="invite" idrefs="th1" sexe="masculin">
        <nompers>
          <prenom>Nicolas</prenom>
          <nomfamille>Mavrikakis</nomfamille>
        </nompers>
      </redacteurchef>
      <redacteurchef typerc="invite" idrefs="th1" sexe="masculin">
        <nompers>
          <prenom>Laurent</prenom>
          <nomfamille>Vernet</nomfamille>
        </nompers>
      </redacteurchef>
      <redacteurchef typerc="regulier" sexe="masculin">
        <nompers>
          <prenom>Serge</prenom>
          <nomfamille>Fisette</nomfamille>
        </nompers>
      </redacteurchef>
    </revue>
    <numero id="espace053">
      <nonumero>99</nonumero>
      <pub>
        <periode>Printemps</periode>
        <annee>2012</annee>
      </pub>
      <pubnum>
        <date typedate="publication">2012-03-26</date>
      </pubnum>
      <grtheme id="th1">
        <theme>De quelques questions (et réponses !) sur la radicalité</theme>
        <themeparal lang="en">A Few Questions (and Answers!) on Radicalness</themeparal>
      </grtheme>
    </numero>
    <editeur>
      <nomorg>Le Centre de diffusion 3D</nomorg>
    </editeur>
    <prod>
      <nomorg>Le Centre de diffusion 3D</nomorg>
    </prod>
    <prodnum>
      <nomorg>Érudit</nomorg>
    </prodnum>
    <diffnum>
      <nomorg>Érudit</nomorg>
    </diffnum>
    <schema nom="Erudit Article" version="3.0.0" lang="fr"/>
    <droitsauteur>Tous droits réservés © <nomorg>Le Centre de diffusion 3D</nomorg>, 2012</droitsauteur>
  </admin>
  <liminaire>
    <grtitre><surtitre>La nécessité de la radicalité (suite)</surtitre><surtitreparal lang="en">The Need to be Radical (continued)</surtitreparal>
                <titre>Haute Culture: General Idea. A Retrospective, 1969-1994</titre>
                <trefbiblio><marquage typemarq="italique">Haute Culture: General Idea. A Retrospective, 1969-1994,</marquage> Art Gallery of Ontario, Toronto, July 30, 2011 – January 1, 2012</trefbiblio>
        </grtitre>
    <grauteur>
      <auteur id="au1">
        <nompers>
          <prenom>Peter</prenom>
          <nomfamille>Dubé</nomfamille>
        </nompers>
      </auteur>
      <auteur id="au2">
        <contribution typecontrib="trl">Traduction :</contribution>
        <nompers>
          <prenom>S.</prenom>
          <nomfamille>F.</nomfamille>
        </nompers>
      </auteur>
    </grauteur>
  </liminaire>
  <corps lang="fr">
    <texte typetexte="libre">

LA NÉCESSITÉ DE LA RADICALITÉ (suite)

THE NEED TO BE RADICAL (continued)

Haute Culture:

General Idea. A Retrospective, 1969-1994

Peter DUBÉ

Réunissant plus de trois cents oeuvres de divers médiums, Haute Culture constitue une rétrospective pertinente de l’abondante production du trio canadien General Idea. Présentée quelque temps après que le décès de deux des membres ait mis fin aux activités du groupe, elle revêt une valeur particulière en permettant de faire le point sur leur parcours dans une perspective historique et généalogique, de réexaminer leur importance dans l’émergence au pays de cette étrange construction qu’est le post-modernisme. En révélant les premiers signes de l’érosion – inéluctable – de ce monolithisme, l’exposition offre aussi l’occasion de découvrir à quel point leur démarche était avant-gardiste – voire prophétique – dans leur manière d’aborder ces divers paradoxes.

D’abord présentée au Musée d’Art moderne de la Ville de Paris, l’exposition torontoise est divisée en cinq volets : « artiste, glamour et processus créatif » ; « culture de masse » ; « architectes/archéologues » ; « sexe et réalité » ; « SIDA ». Tout en constituant un cadre efficace, ces regroupements s’avèrent utiles par leur vastitude et leur mouvance « instabilité » ; ils favorisent des lectures globales plutôt que fragmentées, et cette ouverture est précieuse pour appréhender un si vaste corpus, investi d’une multitude de thèmes, d’images et d’idées qui reviennent de façon obsessive et ludique.

Avec la proéminence de tels leitmotivs, c’est donc sans surprise que la muse – en constante évolution – du groupe, Miss General Idea, se retrouve partout dans la rétrospective. La soi-disant reine de beauté fictive a notamment représenté les toutes premières incarnations de la quête – pour ne pas dire de la fascination – du « glamour » de Felix Partz, Jorge Zontal et AA Bronson. Le trio avait d’ailleurs affirmé sans ambages : « Nous voulions être célèbres ; nous voulions être brillants ; nous voulions être riches. Cela pour dire que nous voulions être artistes… Nous savions qu’en étant célèbres, qu’en étant brillants, nous pourrions prétendre que nous sommes des artistes, et nous le serions 1. » Malgré l’aspect assurément ironique d’un tel propos, leur intérêt pour les surfaces, l’image, la représentation et l’auto-représentation – et leurs effets culturel et politique – traverse toute l’oeuvre du collectif. Dès lors, il était difficile de trouver meilleure incarnation d’un tel intérêt que l’éponyme « Miss ». Le fantôme de l’hypothétique diva hante l’exposition, de la documentation de The Miss General Idea Pageant (1971) et ses performances jusqu’aux faux artefacts qui sont excavés de son pavillon comme dans The Unveiling of the Cornucopia: A Mural Fragment from the Room of Unknown Function in the Villa dei Misteri of the 1984 Miss General Idea Pavilion (1982).

Dans le contexte d’une collaboration artistique où le moi devient forcément une entité partagée, la paradoxale mise au premier plan d’une figure unique en tant qu’incarnation de substitution se révèle l’une des plus belles ironies – au sein d’une démarche qui, au demeurant, en compte beaucoup d’autres. Plus encore : depuis que lui sont attribuées une longue « histoire » ainsi qu’une joyeuse superficialité, Miss GI confirme son statut mythologique même quand elle le subvertit. Des assertions révélatrices de cette lutte dialectique apparaissent clairement dans deux oeuvres qui portent son nom. La première, Miss General Idea Glove Pattern (Form Follows Fetish) (1975) pointe directement la notion d’« auto-confection » en montrant un vêtement complètement inadapté à son corps, le tout accompagné d’un texte sardonique. Artist’s Conception; Miss General Idea 1971 (1971), une autre représentation iconique du personnage, va plus loin puisqu’elle est habillée de vêtements fétichistes et surtout affublée d’un masque. Tout autant amusante que troublante, l’image évoque Pierre Molinier, cet autre auto-transformeur et auto-façonneur. Toutefois, l’ubiquité et la fluidité du personnage Miss General Idea ne sont, pour le groupe, qu’une manière de réitérer leur déploiement stratégique d’iconographies, particulièrement celles qui relèvent de l’identitaire.

Un autre cas est leur recours aux caniches, lesquels agissent aussi comme des dédoublements. Souvent représenté en groupe de trois, le chien est peut-être plus présent encore, plus insistant que Miss General Idea – même si les caniches se retrouvent dans quelques oeuvres de Miss GI, entre autres dans les fresques pseudo archéologiques mentionnées plus haut. Les peintures Mondo Cane Kama Sutra, avec leurs couleurs criardes et leurs représentations formelles minimalistes et provocantes d’accouplements sexuels acrobatiques, incarnent plusieurs des tensions qui sous-tendent l’image. Suggérant en même temps l’homosexualité, l’artifice et quelque chose de fondamentalement totémique, les caniches – peints dans de vives teintes de néon sur fond noir – stupéfient les spectateurs quant à l’impact et à la complexité de leur référentialité.

L’installation/performance de séance/peinture XXX (bleu) (1984) est aussi emblématique. Trois caniches blancs empaillés sont posés devant trois immenses toiles non tendues sur lesquelles on voit de gigantesques « X » bleus. Lors de la performance originale, les caniches ont été trempés dans de la peinture bleue et utilisés pour peindre les motifs. Certes, les références à Yves Klein et à l’aspect très « viril » de l’Action Painting sont manifestes, mais la pièce semble déborder de ces seules références. L’usage constant du chiffre magique trois, les chiens défraîchis mais toujours bien tondus, l’ambiguïté même des « X » (baisers à la fin d’une lettre, cryptogrammes, cibles, croix, symboles de pornographie hard (triple « X ») rendent les oeuvres vibrantes de tensions.

Et, ultimement, c’est cette tension que le spectateur retient de cette magnifique exposition. Tension entre, d’une part, le pur plaisir visuel et, d’autre part, une charge significative dense et – souvent – instable. Certains la percevront dans les autoportraits où le groupe est déguisé tantôt en vampires, docteurs ou caniches (encore une fois), tantôt en bébés phoques ou en poupons souriants bordés avec soin – toujours exécutés avec des surfaces lisses inspirées de la publicité ; d’autres la trouveront dans les dernières oeuvres sur le SIDA dont la puissance émotionnelle est prégnante, sans jamais être amoindrie par l’emprunt aux couleurs et aux formes du très célèbre LOVE d’Indiana. Cette tension se retrouve également dans les vidéos, que l’on pense notamment au mélange d’agression et d’absurdité qui émane de Shut the Fuck Up ! (1985). Dans chaque exemple, l’un des grands plaisirs de General Idea réside invariablement dans les tensions (multiples, plurivalentes) qui s’en dégagent même quand il s’agit d’oeuvres en apparence plus simples.

Il est sûrement significatif que, à l’époque où les politiques identitaires ont commencé à se manifester, General Idea ait trouvé une façon de réaliser des oeuvres qui concernaient l’identité gay, mais sans endosser entièrement aucun de ses modèles, sans jamais investir leur propos de certitudes péremtoires et immuables. Ils ont plutôt retenu certains clichés identitaires et les ont propulsés à l’avant-plan, non seulement pour revendiquer un territoire politique et culturel, mais aussi pour démontrer qu’embrasser une identité est partiellement une affaire de choix et partiellement une affaire de plaisir – sans tenir compte, par exemple, si oui ou non le désir homosexuel, en tant que désir, relève du génétique, du biochimique ou d’autres considérations. Le fait d’être « gay », d’adhérer à une communauté particulière, de privilégier certains manières de vivre, relève assurément d’une décision – une décision basée non seulement sur qui l’on est, mais aussi sur ce que l’on veut faire. GI l’a bien compris et, plus important, il l’a fait indépendamment d’autres considérations – par exemple, que les significations d’un tel désir n’ont pas nécessairement pour origine des attitudes qui sont profondément ancrées chez l’humain. Ce faisant, il pointait l’inévitable impasse de ces politiques culturelles, et ce qu’il y a de malsain à rigidifier toutes catégorisations – leur traitement de l’identité gay n’étant qu’un exemple de la conscience qu’ils avaient de ces questions.

On peut faire des lectures similaires de leur façon d’aborder les médias et la culture populaire, comme le démontre le magazine File. Parler de leur travail en s’attardant uniquement sur l’aspect ironique risque d’en gommer sa dimension plus profonde. Les oeuvres de General Idea sont plus radicales que cela. Elles ne cherchent pas uniquement à parodier l’image, le glamour, la médiation et la représentation, elles veulent aussi en montrer le plaisir et ce, qu’on les aime ou les déteste. Elles clament non seulement leur pouvoir de dénoncer mais aussi celui de réjouir, tout en explorant – avec beaucoup de sérieux – les implications qui y sont sous-jacentes. D’ailleurs, n’ont-ils pas affirmé qu’ils étaient là pour inventer un « simulacre imparfait d’un monde parfait 2 » ! Et, comme le démontre cette rétrospective, ils ont mis l’accent sur les deux termes de l’équation. &lt;

Traduction : S. F.

Haute Culture: General Idea. A Retrospective, 1969-1994 Musée des beaux-arts de l’Ontario, Toronto 30 juillet 2011 – 1er janvier 2012

Écrivain et critique d’art, Peter DUBÉ vit à Montréal. Auteur de quatre ouvrages de fiction, il publiera en 2012 deux nouveaux livres : le roman The City’s Gates (Cormorant Books) et Conjure, un recueil de poèmes en prose (Rebel Satori Press).

ESPACE 99 printemps/spring 2012

GENERAL IDEA, Mondo Cane Kama Sutra, 1984. Détail/detail. Ensemble de dix tableaux, acrylique fluorescente sur toile/Group of ten paintings, fluorescent acrylic on canvas. 243,8 x 304,8 x 10 cm ch/ea. Photo : avec l’aimable autorisation/courtesy Mai 36 Gallery (Zurich) &amp; Esther Schipper Gallery (Berlin).

Featuring more than 300 works in diverse media, Haute Culture is a timely review of the extensive production of General Idea, the Canadian art trio AA Bronson, Felix Partz and Jorge Zontal. Given the lapse of time since the death of two of its members put an end to the group’s work, the exhibition has particular value in allowing us to take stock of the work in an historical and genealogical context, which is to say to reassess its importance in how that most-troubling of constructs, post-modernism, emerged in Canada. And given some signs that said monolith has begun its inevitable erosion, it also creates an opportunity to see just how sharp — and prophetic — General Idea’s play with its inherent paradoxes was.

The show at the Art Gallery of Ontario (AGO) was first presented at the Musée d’art moderne de la Ville de Paris and is organized along five broad thematic divisions: “the artist, glamour and the creative process;” “mass culture;” “architects/archaeologists;” “sex and reality;” and “AIDS.” Such categories, though effective enough as a framework, feel more relevant for their breadth and slipperiness; they enable more open readings, rather than more focused ones, and that open-endedness is invaluable when encountering so vast a body of work inhabited by a handful of obsessively and joyfully reiterated themes, images and ideas.

Given the prominence of such leitmotifs, it comes as no surprise that General Idea’s (GI) perennially mutating muse, Miss General Idea, appears repeatedly in the retrospective. The imaginary beauty queen (of sorts) was among the earliest incarnations of Partz, Zontal and Bronson’s investigation of — not to say fascination with — the idea glamour. The trio was, after all, the author of an early text bluntly stating: “We wanted to be famous; we wanted to be glamorous; we wanted to be rich. That is to say, we wanted to be artists… We knew that if we were famous, if we were glamorous, we could say we were artists, and we would be.” 1 Though that manifesto was certainly ironic, an interest in surfaces, image, representation and self-representation and their cultural and political effects nonetheless runs through the collective’s work. A more effective incarnation of such interest than the eponymous “Miss” could hardly be found. From documentation of The Miss General Idea Pageant (1971) and its performances to faux-artifacts excavated from her pavilion like The Unveiling of the Cornucopia: A Mural Fragment from the Room of Unknown Function in the Villa dei Misteri of the 1984 Miss General Idea Pavilion (1982), the specter of this hypothetical diva haunts the show.

In the context of an artistic collaboration that so forcefully presented itself as a shared identity, the paradoxical foregrounding of a single figure as an alternate incarnation constitutes one of the most delightful ironies in a career filled with them. Moreover, since she was accorded both a profound “history” and a gleeful superficiality, she asserts her mythological status even while subverting it. Telling assertions of that dialectical tug are especially clear in two of the works bearing her name. The first, Miss General Idea Glove Pattern (Form Follows Fetish) (1975) affirms the notion of self-fashioning in a direct way by illustrating a garment completely unsuited to the body and accompanying it with a sardonic text. Artist’s Conception; Miss General Idea 1971 (1971), a now iconic depiction of the character, goes further, clothing the depicted figure in fetishistic garments and, most tellingly of all, a mask. Both witty and troubling, the image evokes the work of that other self-transforming self-fashioner, Pierre Molinier. The ubiquity and fluidity of the Miss General Idea character is, however, simply one iteration of the group’s strategic deployment of iconographies, particularly identitarian ones.

The artists’ use of the poodle is another case. Another suggestive stand-in for the artists, frequently appearing in groups of three, the dog may be even more present, more insistent than Miss General Idea herself. Indeed poodles feature in some of the Miss GI works, notably the pseudo-archeological frescoes mentioned above. The Mondo Cane Kama Sutra paintings with their garish colours, formal reduction and provocative depictions of acrobatic sexual couplings embody many of the pressures inherent in the image. Simultaneously suggesting homosexuality, artifice and something primordially totemic, the outlined poodles –– painted in vivid neon hues against black backgrounds –– are arresting in their impact and complex in their referentiality. The installation/performance record/painting XXX (bleu) (1984) is also emblematic; three stuffed white poodles stand before three large unstretched canvases bearing blue Xs. The poodles were dipped in blue paint and used to paint the glyphs in the original performance. The reference to Klein and a vehemently butch form of Action Painting are clear, but the piece itself seems to escape such limited references. General Idea’s constant use of the magic number three, the soiled but still prissily clipped dogs, the ambiguity of the Xs themselves (kisses at the end of a letter, ciphers, targets, crosses, shorthand for hardcore or “triple x” pornography), makes the work quiver with tension.

And, ultimately, such tension — the fraught joining of a dense, frequently unstable charge of meaning to sheer visual pleasure — is what a viewer takes away from this almost entirely successful exhibition. One finds it in the group self-portraits on display with their many guises: vampires, doctors, poodles (once again), baby seals, smiling children safely tucked-in, all executed with slick, advertising-inspired surfaces; and one finds it in the later AIDS work whose emotional power is leavened, though never softened, by its borrowing of colours and form from Indiana’s too familiar LOVE. It runs through the videos as well; think of the marriage of aggression and absurdity that powers “Shut the Fuck Up!” (1985). In each instance, one of the great pleasures of General Idea consistently lies in the stresses (multiple, multivalent) that animate even its most simple appearing works.

It is certainly significant that, at the very moment identity politics were beginning their ascent, General Idea found a way to make work that addressed gay identity while not entirely endorsing any of its models, without affirming certainty and fixity. They took the clichés of identitary signifiers and insistently foregrounded them not simply to claim political and cultural territory, but to make clear that embracing an identity is at least partly a choice, and at least partly about pleasure. Regardless of whether or not, for example, homosexual desire as desire is genetically, biochemically or otherwise hardwired, being “gay,” making a place for oneself in a particular community, embracing certain patterns of living, is certainly a choice––a choice based not simply on who we are, but on what we like to do. GI understood this, and more importantly got that regardless of other considerations, the meanings of such desire’s signifiers certainly aren’t hardwired. They saw the inevitable dead-end of such cultural politics before most, and they understood what was unhealthy in any hardening of categories, because their treatment of gay identity is just one instance of their consciousness of such questions.

Similar readings of their approach to media and popular culture (or other things) could be made; “File” magazine might serve as a starting point. That’s why readings of their work that focus merely on its ironies perhaps miss some of its deeper power. General Idea’s work is more radical than that; it not only makes fun of images, glamour, mediation, representation, it acknowledges that they are fun, and that we love them even as we despise them. The work acknowledges not merely their power to repress, but their power to rejoice. And it explores the — very serious — implications of that. After all, they also wrote that they were out to create “an imperfect simulacrum of a perfect world,” 2 and as this retrospective suggests, the emphasis was on both terms in that particular equation. &lt;

Haute Culture: General Idea. A Retrospective, 1969-1994 Art Gallery of Ontario, Toronto July 30, 2011 – January 1, 2012

Peter DUBÉ is a Montreal-based writer and cultural critic. The author of four books of fiction, he has two new works scheduled for publication this year: the novel The City’s Gates (Cormorant Books) and Conjure, a volume of prose poems (Rebel Satori Press.)

GENERAL IDEA, The Miss General Idea Gown, 1971. Robe de « taffeta » d’acétate cellulose avec typographie sur étiquette en papier/ Cellulose acetate “taffeta” dress with letterpress on paper tag. 123 x 135 cm. Don/Gift of AA Bronson, 1998. Photo : avec l’aimable autorisation/courtesy the Estate of General Idea and the Art Gallery of Ontario.

ESPACE 99 printemps/spring 2012  

GENERAL IDEA, AIDS (vue de l’installation /installation view), 1987. Papier peint sérigraphié /Silkscreen wallpaper. Dimensions variables / Various dimensions; AIDS (vue de l’installation/installation view), 1988. Acrylique sur toile/Acrylic on canvas. 243,7 x 243,7 cm. Don/Gift of Robert and Lynn Simpson, 1997. Photo : Carlo Catenazzi. Avec l’aimable autorisation/courtesy the Estate of General Idea and the Art Gallery of Ontario.

&gt; GENERAL IDEA, Baby Makes 3, 1984-1989. Impression chromogénique/Chromogenic print. 76,2 x 63,5 cm. Collection Fonds national d’art contemporain, France. Photo : avec l’aimable autorisation / courtesy the Estate of General Idea and the Art Gallery of Ontario.

&gt; &gt; GENERAL IDEA, Playing Doctor, 1992. Impression chromogénique / Chromogenic print. 76,2 x 53,3 cm. Photo : avec l’aimable autorisation/ courtesy the Estate of General Idea and the Art Gallery of Ontario.

GENERAL IDEA, Evidence of Body Binding, 1971. Quinze transparents n/b dans des boîtes lumineuses en acier /15 b&amp;w transparencies in steel light boxes. 20,7 x 30,9 x 8,5 cm/each. Collection : Musée des beaux-arts du Canada / National Gallery of Canada. Photo : avec l’aimable autorisation / courtesy the Estate of General Idea and the Art Gallery of Ontario.

ESPACE 99 printemps/spring 2012  

ESPACE 99 printemps/spring 2012

Notes

1. Extrait du catalogue (notre traduction) / Cited in the exhibition catalogue, General Idea, Frédéric Bonnet (ed.), Zurich, JRP/Ringier, 2011, p. 19.

2. Ibid., p. 19. (notre traduction).

GENERAL IDEA, Lux-On, 1974. Sérigraphie sur papier / Screenprint on paper. 46,4 x 58 cm. Photo : avec l’aimable autorisation /courtesy the Estate of General Idea and the Art Gallery of Ontario.

GENERAL IDEA, Manipulating the Self, 1973. Lithographie couleurs sur papier / Offset colour lithograph on paper. 73,7 x 58,4 cm. Acquise en 1974 / Purchased 1974. Photo : avec l’aimable autorisation /courtesy the Estate of General Idea and the Art Gallery of Ontario.
</texte>
  </corps>
  <partiesann lang="fr">
    <grnotebio>
      <notebio id="nb1" idrefs="au1 au2" lang="fr">
        <alinea>Écrivain et critique d’art, <marquage typemarq="gras">Peter DUBÉ</marquage> vit à Montréal. Auteur de quatre ouvrages de fiction, il publiera en 2012 deux nouveaux livres ;: le roman The City’s Gates (Cormorant Books) et Conjure, un recueil de poèmes en prose (Rebel Satori Press).</alinea>
      </notebio>
    </grnotebio>
  </partiesann>
  <partiesann lang="en">
    <grnotebio>
      <notebio id="nb2" idrefs="au1 au2" lang="en">
        <alinea><marquage typemarq="gras">Peter DUBÉ</marquage> is a Montreal-based writer and cultural critic. The author of four books of fiction, he has two new works scheduled for publication this year: the novel The City’s Gates (Cormorant Books) and Conjure, a volume of prose poems (Rebel Satori Press.)</alinea>
      </notebio>
    </grnotebio>
  </partiesann>
</article>
