<article xmlns="http://www.erudit.org/xsd/article" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.erudit.org/xsd/article http://www.erudit.org/xsd/article/3.0.0/eruditarticle.xsd" qualtraitement="minimal" idproprio="66177ac" typeart="article" lang="fr en" ordseq="7" idref="th1">
  <admin>
    <infoarticle>
      <pagination>
            <ppage>26</ppage>
            <dpage>28</dpage>
            
            
            
        </pagination>
    </infoarticle>
    <revue id="espace1041666" lang="fr en">
      <titrerev>Espace Sculpture</titrerev>
      <titrerevabr>espace</titrerevabr>
      <idissn>0821-9222</idissn>
      <idissnnum>1923-2551</idissnnum>
      <directeur sexe="masculin">
        <nompers>
          <prenom>Serge</prenom>
          <nomfamille>Fisette</nomfamille>
        </nompers>
      </directeur>
      <redacteurchef typerc="invite" idrefs="th1" sexe="masculin">
        <nompers>
          <prenom>Nicolas</prenom>
          <nomfamille>Mavrikakis</nomfamille>
        </nompers>
      </redacteurchef>
      <redacteurchef typerc="invite" idrefs="th1" sexe="masculin">
        <nompers>
          <prenom>Laurent</prenom>
          <nomfamille>Vernet</nomfamille>
        </nompers>
      </redacteurchef>
      <redacteurchef typerc="regulier" sexe="masculin">
        <nompers>
          <prenom>Serge</prenom>
          <nomfamille>Fisette</nomfamille>
        </nompers>
      </redacteurchef>
    </revue>
    <numero id="espace053">
      <nonumero>99</nonumero>
      <pub>
        <periode>Printemps</periode>
        <annee>2012</annee>
      </pub>
      <pubnum>
        <date typedate="publication">2012-03-26</date>
      </pubnum>
      <grtheme id="th1">
        <theme>De quelques questions (et réponses !) sur la radicalité</theme>
        <themeparal lang="en">A Few Questions (and Answers!) on Radicalness</themeparal>
      </grtheme>
    </numero>
    <editeur>
      <nomorg>Le Centre de diffusion 3D</nomorg>
    </editeur>
    <prod>
      <nomorg>Le Centre de diffusion 3D</nomorg>
    </prod>
    <prodnum>
      <nomorg>Érudit</nomorg>
    </prodnum>
    <diffnum>
      <nomorg>Érudit</nomorg>
    </diffnum>
    <schema nom="Erudit Article" version="3.0.0" lang="fr"/>
    <droitsauteur>Tous droits réservés © <nomorg>Le Centre de diffusion 3D</nomorg>, 2012</droitsauteur>
  </admin>
  <liminaire>
    <grtitre><surtitre>La nécessité de la radicalité (suite)</surtitre><surtitreparal lang="en">The Need to be Radical (continued)</surtitreparal>
                <titre>Un art radical ?</titre>
                <titreparal lang="en">Radical Art?</titreparal>
        </grtitre>
    <grauteur>
      <auteur id="au1">
        <nompers>
          <prenom>Julian</prenom>
          <nomfamille>Stallabrass</nomfamille>
        </nompers>
      </auteur>
      <auteur id="au2">
        <contribution typecontrib="trl">Traduction :</contribution>
        <nompers>
          <prenom>Benoît</prenom>
          <nomfamille>Faucher</nomfamille>
        </nompers>
      </auteur>
    </grauteur>
  </liminaire>
  <corps lang="fr">
    <texte typetexte="libre">LA NÉCESSITÉ DE LA RADICALITÉ (suite)

THE NEED TO BE RADICAL (continued)

Un art radical ?

Julian STALLABRASS

Si quelqu’un de radical examinait les éléments les plus publicisés de la scène artistique contemporaine, on comprendrait qu’il développe un certain épuisement, voire un brin de dépression ou de cynisme. Alors que la fin du boom catastrophique des années 2000 a grandement déprécié les prix et le prestige des vedettes les plus « bancables » et les plus clinquantes, plusieurs investisseurs continuent d’utiliser l’art (en particulier les toiles d’artistes bien établis) comme protection contre la chute d’autres actions. Et les sociétés de ventes aux enchères ne cessent de claironner les prix records atteints de temps à autre. Les musées poursuivent leur connivence avec les banques et les compagnies de pétrole, investissant pour éviter de potentielles pertes de réputation. Des artistes-marques qui, depuis longtemps, ennuient les spectateurs avec leurs performances « programmées » et leurs produits standardisés continuent à retenir l’attention des médias de masse.

Pourtant, sous ce lustre publicitaire se produisent des développements extraordinaires aux conséquences radicales. Premièrement, il y une relance de la vidéo et de la photo documentaire, des médiums négligés par le milieu artistique au cours des années 1980 et pour la majeure partie des années 1990. Plusieurs de ces oeuvres sont « proprettes », destinées au marché, mais la majorité d’entre elles trouvent leur place sur la scène des biennales – où l’on est moins intéressé à décorer le quotidien des milliardaires. De vielles critiques postmodernes concernant la « politique de représentation » ont été combinées avec une pensée sophistiquée sur la représentation de la politique afin de produire des oeuvres complexes ayant une visée brechtienne. Des oeuvres de Hito Steyerl, Omer Fast, Silvia Kolbowksi et de plusieurs autres combinent leur puissance politique à une mise en scène engageante et à une forte pulsion narrative.

Deuxièmement, et de façon tout aussi remarquable, il existe de nombreuses tentatives visant à impliquer activement divers publics dans l’art. Ces oeuvres se déploient dans diverses pratiques englobées sous le terme « esthétique relationnelle » de Nicolas Bourriaud. Ici aussi, des considérations radicales se sont propagées : l’art peut commenter et même atténuer l’aliénation sociale ; il peut constituer une réponse à cette attitude répandue qui consiste à traiter les choses et les gens uniquement en fonction de leur utilité ; l’art peut promouvoir des idéaux positifs en ce qui a trait aux phénomènes de sauvegarde, d’actions collectives, d’égalité et de démocratie. Beaucoup de ces oeuvres utilisent l’ironie et, au moyen de l’utopie et de la réflexion, créent un contraste entre ces idéaux et la dégradation de nos environnements sociaux, politiques et économiques – se moquant ainsi des grandes distances qui restent à parcourir pour véritablement concrétiser ces aspirations radicales. Autant les oeuvres documentaires que l’art qui traite des relations sociales font prendre conscience de l’oppression et de l’aliénation ambiante. Ces deux formes d’art désignent implicitement ces modèles que nous savons être oppressifs et aliénants, sans toutefois indiquer clairement comment les choses pourraient changer.

Ainsi, durant un certain temps, l’art s’est embourbé dans cette impasse : le monde artistique divisé entre ce qui sert le marché en fournissant des produits commerciaux, et ce qui sert d’autres publics à l’aide de documentaires et d’expériences sociales. Or, depuis les cinq dernières années, cette situation s’est modifiée, ébranlée par deux changements profonds ayant transformé la scène artistique. Le premier est la popularité grandissante des médias sociaux qui ont permis à des millions de gens de créer et d’exposer à un large public leurs produits culturels – lesquels, dans plusieurs cas, s’apparentent à de l’art. Les artistes ont fait de même. Ils ont mis en ligne des versions (numériques) de leurs productions, brisant ainsi le monopole des présentations dans le cube blanc du musée ou de la galerie. Un exemple : il est maintenant possible d’enseigner de façon adéquate une histoire de la vidéo d’art à partir de YouTube, alors que, il n’y a pas si longtemps, les vidéos d’artistes étaient confinées dans des archives ou exclusivement distribuées dans des éditions limitées réservées aux collections privées et aux musées. Dans cette expansion massive de la production et de la diffusion culturelles, on peut discerner un étrange accomplissement technologique des attentes élevées de Walter Benjamin envers l’art radical : à savoir que celui-ci soit évalué non seulement pour son contenu politique, mais aussi pour sa capacité à changer les fondements mêmes du rapport entre l’oeuvre et le public, donnant ainsi à ce dernier les outils pour agir.

Devant les injustices sociales de plus en plus importantes imposées par les gouvernements en réponse à la crise financière, un second changement s’est produit : l’opposition politique est graduellement devenue un mouvement global. Certaines tactiques utopistes de l’esthétique relationnelle sont maintenant descendues dans la rue, particulièrement dans les camps érigés par le mouvement des indignés. Le recours au documentaire est maintenant partout évident : autant dans la propagande virale mise en place par les protestataires, que dans la présence de caméras qui surveillent et refrènent les actions de l’État et des forces policières, constamment sous la surveillance des diffusions en réseau. La voie vers le changement n’est peut-être pas encore claire, mais le monopole que l’orthodoxie néolibérale détenait sur l’imagination et la pensée est maintenant mis en pièces.

L’art et la culture qui émergent de ces mouvements seront faits par des collectifs et des forces démocratiques en interaction. Les produits marchands en vogue au sein du milieu artistique, ainsi que les institutions qui les soutiennent, cherchent à convaincre les spectateurs qu’ils sont uniques, exceptionnels, au-delà du commun, signes de la liberté d’expression et transcendants – et que ces valeurs sont inhérentes à l’objet adoré. La culture radicale se tiendra peut-être à l’écart de chacune de ces caractéristiques et des mythes qui les accompagnent. Plutôt que d’être uniques, les oeuvres radicales seront populaires et typiques ; plutôt qu’individuelles, elles seront collectives (délaissant l’idée de valeur marchande associée à l’oeuvre, souvent réduite à un nom ou à une marque) ; plutôt que de correspondre aux idéaux bourgeois de l’individu libre et solitaire, elles seront utilisées et liées au social ; elles seront ouvertes à la compréhension publique, délestées de l’idéologie quasi mystique souvent présente dans le langage artistique (liminaire, rhizomatique, sublime, ineffable, etc.). Ces oeuvres se manifesteront beaucoup moins en tant qu’objets immuables et protégés du public ; elles seront plutôt un des éléments du flot d’information et d’objets temporaires qui traverseront l’espace public en encourageant le dialogue, l’emprunt et la croissance. Ainsi, les radicaux pourront choisir de faire, de partager, de parler, d’enseigner et de répondre aux oeuvres de façon collective ; de rendre leurs travaux utiles. De cette activité et de ce dialogue collectif, de cette expression de la démocratie directe, on pourra peut-être voir émerger – sur une échelle tant locale que globale – un art sans précédent qui dialoguera véritablement au lieu de simplement servir de transmetteur. &lt;

Traduction : Benoît Faucher.

Julian STALLABRASS est écrivain, commissaire, photographe et conférencier. Il enseigne l’histoire de l’art au Courtland Institute of Art, et il est l’auteur de Art Incorporated publié chez Oxford University Press (2004) ; Internet Art: The Online Clash Between Culture and Commerce, Tate Publishing, Londres (2003) ; Paris Pictured, Royal Academy of Arts, Londres (2002) ; High Art Lite: British Art in the 1990s, Verso, Londres (1999) et Gargantua: Manufactured Mass Culture, Verso, Londres (1996). Il est coéditeur de Ground Control: Technology and Utopia, Black Dog Publishing, Londres (1997), Occupational Hazard: Critical Writing on Recent British Art, Black Dog Publishing, Londres (1998), et Locus Solus: Technology, Identity and Site in Contemporary Art, Black Dog Publishing, Londres (1999). Il rédige des critiques d’art dans diverses publications, dont Tate, Art Monthly et New Statesman. Il fait partie du comité de rédaction de Art History, New Left Review et Third Text. Il a été commissaire de la Brighton Photo Biennial en 2008, « Memory of Fire: Images of War and the War of Images ».

ESPACE 99 printemps/spring 2012

Radical Art?

Surveying the best-publicized parts of the contemporary art scene, any radical could be forgiven a touch of weary depression and cynicism. While the end of the dramatic boom of the mid 2000s dealt heavy blows to the prices and prestige of some of the most bankable and meretricious stars, many investors still use art (especially painting by well-established figures) as a hedge against the fall of other stocks, and the auction houses still loudly trumpet the occasional record price. The museums still cosy up to banks and oil companies, weighing cash against loss of reputation. Artist-brands, who have long bored viewers with their robotic performances and standardized products, still hog the attention of the mass media.

Yet just beneath the surface of that sheen of publicity, extraordinary developments have been unfolding, which bear on radical concerns. First, there is the revival of documentary video and photography, after their long neglect in the art world through the 1980s and much of the 1990s. Some of it is slickly made with an eye on the market, but much more finds its destination on the biennial scene, where decorating the lives of billionaires is less of a concern. Old postmodern critiques of the ‘politics of representation’ have been fused with sophisticated thinking about the representation of politics to deliver complex works with a Brechtian aim. Pieces by Hito Steyerl, Omer Fast, Silvia Kolbowksi and many others combine their powerful politics with compelling staging and narrative drive.

Second, and equally prominent are the efforts to involve audiences actively in art works, from the range of practices captured by Nicolas Bourriaud’s term ‘relational aesthetics’ onwards. Here, too, radical concerns are aired: that art should comment on and even try to ameliorate social alienation; that it be a response to treating things and people as nothing more than useful objects; that art may hold out positive ideals of conversation, collective action, equality and democracy. Much of this art holds irony in reserve, and with self-consciously utopian gestures, contrasts those ideals against the degraded reality of our social, political and economic environment, mocking radical aspirations with the vast distances yet to travel. Both the documentary work and the art that deals with social relations raise awareness of oppression and alienation, and gesture implicitly at the ideals by which we recognise them as oppressive and alienating, yet with little clear sense of how things could change.

So, for a quite a while, art tarried at that terminus — with the art world split between that which served the market with branded goods, and that which served other audiences with documentaries and social experiments — yet over the last five years that stasis crumbled as two profound changes transformed the field against which art is set. The first is the rise of social media, which has brought millions of people to make and publicly exhibit their cultural products — many of which look like art — to large audiences. Artists do the same, uploading versions of their (in any case digital) products and eroding the exclusivity of white cube display. While artists’ videos, for example, were once locked away in archives and limited-edition media in private collections and museums, a pretty decent history of video art can now be taught from YouTube. In this massive expansion of the production and publishing of culture, we can see a strange technological fulfilment of Walter Benjamin’s hard demand of radical art: that it should be judged, not merely by its political content, but by the extent to which it changed the grounds on which audiences related to works of art, giving them the tools with which to act.

The second change is that, as governments imposed greater injustices in response to the financial crisis, political opposition gradually grew into a global movement. Some of the utopian tactics of relational aesthetics are now tried out in the street, particularly in the encampments of the occupations. The uses of documentary are everywhere apparent, in the viral propaganda of the protestors, and in the restraints that the presence of so many lenses puts on the actions of the state and the police, who are continually watched by networked cameras. The path to change may not yet be clear, but the monopoly that neoliberal orthodoxy had on imagination and thought has been shattered.

The art and culture that emerges from these movements will be made by collective and democratic forces interacting. Mainstream, marketised products of the art world, and the institutions that surround them, seek to convince viewers that they are individual, exceptional, above vulgar use, freely expressed and transcendent — and that these values inhere in treasured objects. Perhaps radical culture will stand apart from each of these qualities and their accompanying myths. Rather than being exceptional, radical works of art will be popular and typical; rather than individual, they will be collective (pressing down on the market value of art works that are reducible to name and brand); rather than pretending to the bourgeois ideal of the free, solitary individual, they will be put to use and bound to the social; they will be open to public understanding, unarmoured with the quasi-mystical ideology of much art language (liminal, abject, rhizomatic, sublime, ineffable, etc.). These works may be found less as objects conserved against change and protected from public reaction, than as the flow of data and temporary objects across public space, which encourage dialogue, borrowing and improvement. So radicals may choose to make, share, talk, teach and respond to work collectively, and put their work to use. Out of collective action, dialogue and the exercise of direct democracy, we may see emerge — on a local and global scale — an unprecedented art that does not broadcast but converses. &lt;

Julian STALLABRASS is a writer, curator, photographer and lecturer. He is a professor of art history at the Courtauld Institute of Art, and is the author of Art Incorporated, Oxford University Press 2004, Internet Art: The Online Clash Between Culture and Commerce, Tate Publishing, London 2003; Paris Pictured, Royal Academy of Arts, London 2002; High Art Lite: British Art in the 1990s, Verso, London 1999 and Gargantua: Manufactured Mass Culture, Verso, London 1996; he is the co-editor of Ground Control: Technology and Utopia, Black Dog Publishing, London 1997, Occupational Hazard: Critical Writing on Recent British Art, Black Dog Publishing, London 1998, and Locus Solus: Technology, Identity and Site in Contemporary Art, Black Dog Publishing, London 1999. He has written art criticism regularly for publications such as Tate, Art Monthly and the New Statesman, and is an editorial board member of Art History, New Left Review and Third Text. He curated the 2008 Brighton Photo Biennial, ‘Memory of Fire: Images of War and the War of Images.’

Omer FAST, 5,000 Feet is the Best, 2011. Video, couleurs, son/ Video, colour, sound. 30 min. Édition : 6 (+ 2 E.A.). Photo : avec l’aimable autorisation de l’artiste, gb agency, Paris et Arratia Beer, Berlin /Courtesy the artist, gb agency, Paris and Arratia Beer, Berlin.

ESPACE 99 printemps/spring 2012  

ESPACE 99 printemps/spring 2012

Silvia KOLBOWSKI, A few howls again?, 2010. image tirée de la vidéo en boucle / video loop; 10 mins.; video still. Photo : avec l’aimable autorisation de l’artiste / Courtesy the artist.
</texte>
  </corps>
  <partiesann lang="fr">
    <grnotebio>
      <notebio id="nb1" idrefs="au1 au2" lang="fr">
        <alinea><marquage typemarq="gras">Julian STALLABRASS</marquage> est écrivain, commissaire, photographe et conférencier. Il enseigne l’histoire de l’art au Courtland Institute of Art, et il est l’auteur de Art Incorporated publié chez Oxford University Press (2004) ; Internet Art: The Online Clash Between Culture and Commerce, Tate Publishing, Londres (2003) ; Paris Pictured, Royal Academy of Arts, Londres (2002) ; High Art Lite: British Art in the 1990s, Verso, Londres (1999) et Gargantua: Manufactured Mass Culture, Verso, Londres (1996). Il est coéditeur de Ground Control: Technology and Utopia, Black Dog Publishing, Londres (1997), Occupational Hazard: Critical Writing on Recent British Art, Black Dog Publishing, Londres (1998), et Locus Solus: Technology, Identity and Site in Contemporary Art, Black Dog Publishing, Londres (1999). Il rédige des critiques d’art dans diverses publications, dont Tate, Art Monthly et New Statesman. Il fait partie du comité de rédaction de Art History, New Left Review et Third Text. Il a été commissaire de la Brighton Photo Biennial en 2008, « Memory of Fire: Images of War and the War of Images ».</alinea>
      </notebio>
    </grnotebio>
  </partiesann>
  <partiesann lang="en">
    <grnotebio>
      <notebio id="nb2" idrefs="au1 au2" lang="en">
        <alinea><marquage typemarq="gras">Julian STALLABRASS</marquage> is a writer, curator, photographer and lecturer. He is a professor of art history at the Courtauld Institute of Art, and is the author of Art Incorporated, Oxford University Press 2004, Internet Art: The Online Clash Between Culture and Commerce, Tate Publishing, London 2003; Paris Pictured, Royal Academy of Arts, London 2002; High Art Lite: British Art in the 1990s, Verso, London 1999 and Gargantua: Manufactured Mass Culture, Verso, London 1996; he is the co-editor of Ground Control: Technology and Utopia, Black Dog Publishing, London 1997, Occupational Hazard: Critical Writing on Recent British Art, Black Dog Publishing, London 1998, and Locus Solus: Technology, Identity and Site in Contemporary Art, Black Dog Publishing, London 1999. He has written art criticism regularly for publications such as Tate, Art Monthly and the New Statesman, and is an editorial board member of Art History, New Left Review and Third Text. He curated the 2008 Brighton Photo Biennial, ‘Memory of Fire: Images of War and the War of Images.’</alinea>
      </notebio>
    </grnotebio>
  </partiesann>
</article>
